- Hey ladies and gentlemen
and welcome to the lesson on
Designing Above Your Level.
So all I mean by
designing above your level
is making the most of the
time in which you're designing
or learning about design so
that you can make progress
as rapidly as possible and quickly achieve
a much higher level than
someone who's spending
say the same number of
hours working as you.
These are the three
things that I have learned
that probably have helped
me learn the fastest
the most over my career.
And I just want to
stress at the beginning,
they're not, two of them are not easy.
One of them is kind of easy
but two of them are not easy.
So they require sustained mental effort
but if you can do these things
and get in these habits,
you will learn quicker and
progress more efficiently.
So the first lesson is something
that I call fail left, fail right.
And this lesson begins with a story.
So when I was in college,
I learned how to unicycle.
College was definitely a time
of questionable decisions,
unicycling was one of these decisions
and yet it was a ton of fun.
The Unicycle Group met every Thursday
at midnight and one
particular Thursday at 12:30,
technically Friday morning.
I was kind of stuck in my
unicycling progression.
So what was happening was I realized
that every time I tried to unicycle,
I would maybe pedal for one,
one and a half, maybe two cycles
but then I would fall off,
and I would always fall off such that
I was going forward and the unicycle
would get shoved out behind
me and it would go backwards.
And one of my friends was watching me
and she noticed kind of what was happening
and she told me some advice,
which I think is probably the best maxim
for rapid skill development
that I've ever heard.
And she just said,
"Hey, you know what?
You should try to alternate
between falling off forwards
and falling off backwards."
That was it.
That was all she said.
And all she was saying was
that if I fell off forward
such that I go forwards in
the unicycle goes backwards
then the next time I should try
and kind of lean back a little bit
such that when I fall off,
I actually fall off backwards
and the unicycle goes off forwards.
And when you fall off a unicycle,
the unicycle basically he was always going
in the opposite direction as you,
at least if you're falling
off backwards or forwards
but the point was,
if you always fall off the same direction,
what is your body learning?
It's just learning how to
fall off in that direction.
It's just learning how to fail in one way.
But if you force your body
to alternate failing
between two different ways,
you can't help but start to pick up
at this unconscious level
the acceptable range
of values in between
failure in one direction
and failure in the other direction.
So if you fail forward
and then fail backward,
at some point your body
just sort of learns
where it can be stable on the unicycle.
So I did that 20 times,
falling forwards and
then falling backwards.
And I probably made more
progress in 10 minutes
than I had made an hours
of unicycling before that.
So great, you might be saying
how does this apply to design?
Well, I promise it does.
Here is an example app.
This is based on something
that I was working on with a client
and it's just sort of a landing page
for some app that
someone might sign up for
for hotel management software.
All of that is not necessarily important.
What is important is that
we have this headline,
Effortlessly Unify Everyone in Your Hotel
and we wanna put it
somewhere on this page.
Okay.
So let's go ahead and do this.
And sort of the naive approach might be
we're gonna make it white text
so we wanna darker background.
So maybe I'll make it black.
I'll press eight for 80%
opacity, maybe seven is better.
I'll have to kind of drag this text in,
I'm gonna make the text white.
Good, it's at the beginning.
And how big do I make it?
I don't know, like 32
sounds like a good tech size
and boom!
There we go.
Just make that a little bit
bigger and call it a day.
And we're set, right?
No.
This is exactly how I
don't want you to design,
what I want you to do instead
in order to learn as quickly as possible
is any time you kind of
take a guess at some value,
yeah, you can eyeball it
but if you're really
wondering about something,
try and explore the range of values
that are too much in either direction.
So if 32 looks like a good header,
maybe, you know I might say,
Oh, 24 that's kind of maybe a bit small
but sort of a decent header.
Then I'm gonna try and figure out like,
what is too big?
Like is 50 too big?
Hmm.
You know what?
This is pretty big and if I used it,
I might have to kind of rearrange
how the image worked in the design here.
But even at 50, I feel like
I could kinda maybe take one shape
and sort of subtract it
out from another one.
Yeah.
And then I have sort of this design
I don't know why my
texts just changed color
that's not what I meant to do.
but then I sort of have this cutoff
where the rectangle image is just
below the text and so on.
So 50 definitely doesn't feel too big
but what if I tried
something like a hundred?
Oh yeah, this for sure is too big.
There's almost no way that I'd be able
to make texts this big work in my design.
And even if I make it, you know, 70 or 80
this still just feels super, super big.
So what I've done is I sorta said,
okay, 50 seems to be about
the biggest I wanna make it,
maybe 30 is like the smallest
it could potentially be
but because I've established
this range of acceptable values,
I have something to experiment with.
I don't just have one
value to go on and I say,
yeah, that's that.
The truth is I'm just gonna
come up with different ideas
as I sort of explore that
range of acceptable values
and some of those ideas might be the ones
I ultimately wanna run with.
If I had just said,
Hey, what's a good size?
32 is a good size and kept it at that,
I never would have
necessarily tried an idea
where the size is 50
and the background works
in a slightly different way here.
Okay, the second idea is
actually kind of related
to the first and I call it Julie's Method.
It's named after Julie Zhuo,
who is the VP design at Facebook.
So, you know, no big deal
in the design industry.
Anyhow, I stole this idea from her
and I named it after her
without her permission.
One thing that she has said is,
"if you have literally tried
every possible variation,
you will have come across
the best solution."
And this might sound exhausting.
Like I'm trying to get
you to create millions
of different variations
of everything you do.
That's not the case.
It's really not about literally trying
every possible variation.
It's about trying everything
that you think might make sense,
just duplicate your frame, your art board
and see how it looks
and then keep doing that
so that you can compare
different variations that you do.
So in this example, you
know, maybe I would say
this is cool but one thing
I wanna see is how it looks
if the headline is just on one line.
And Julie's Method says
what you shouldn't do is
just kind of change one thing
and then hope it looks good
but not really have a good
way to get back to it.
So this is just one little
tweak that I could make
and compare between the
two different frames.
But the whole idea here is
everything that I think of.
I shouldn't be afraid to try it.
So I think as Designers we sort of can get
into this rut where we imagine
what might be a good idea
but we don't actually implement it.
Cause that would be a lot of work.
And instead what I want
to encourage you to do
is when you do think of some other idea
and you wanna see how it looks,
just duplicate your frame
and design it, make it happen
because you can't really
evaluate it in your head.
You have to see it in front of you.
This is exactly what Julie Zhuo has found
that great designers
creating great designs.
They're doing far more
iterations than you might expect
cause the final product,
you don't see all the other iterations.
You only see the finished thing
and you know it it's good.
Well, what we want to do
is when we're designing,
we wanna resist the urge to
sort of rest on our laurels
that we came up with a design
and instead keep churning
out every little variation
that we can think of
and see what looks even better than that.
And to be fair, this is not easy.
It takes sustained mental
effort to generate variation
after variation and then
constantly be tweaking.
It's far easier to look at something
that's like half done,
take a sip of your coffee
just kind of wait for it to
speak to you on how to fix it.
But it's not gonna say anything,
you have to get in there
and do it yourself.
And look at this.
We ended up with a ton of iterations
even for something simpler,
but we've come up with a bunch of ideas
that we never would've seen
if we had just sort of rested
on our laurels after
the very first design.
And here's the thing about doing this,
if you are iterating like this for a while
just crazily coming up with new concepts,
trying out various things
you're going to fry your brain in no time,
you won't even,
I mean, unless you're superhuman,
you can't do this for eight hours.
I find that five or six hours
is about as far as I can get
if I'm really focused on
UI design or UX design
and that's where the
third tip comes into play.
All right?
And the third way to
design above your level
and I'll admit this is a little
bit boring, but it's true
you need to sleep on it.
The thing with UI design is
it's never a one day job.
You might have some project
and you crank away at it for two hours
and your brain might be
feeling a little bit fried
when you look at your designs,
you can't quite tell if they're that good
or if you like them that much
or what you should change
and you're just all out of ideas.
I guarantee you go get some sleep,
come out the next morning, open it up
and you're gonna instantly
have an opinion on it.
You're gonna know what to change
or you're gonna know
exactly how much you like it
or what's working and what's not working.
There is something magical about sleep
in helping you identify what part
of your creative endeavors
are working and what's not.
I found the same thing is
true with editing my writing,
editing songs that I've written,
you have to make it one day
and edit it the next or a few
days later or whatever it is
but expect that same thing with UI design.
It's never a one day job
and this might seem like
bad news if you're in a rush
but ultimately it's going
to make you more efficient.
If you know, you're at
the end of your ability
to think creatively on one day,
you can just go do something else,
check your email, get a coffee whatever
and you can come back the next day
when you're feeling more recharged,
you're definitely gonna
be making the best use
of your time doing that and
you're not gonna feel like
you're banging your
head up against a wall.
So for today's homework,
I want you to integrate all three
of the lessons that we talked about.
I'm gonna give you a design
that you can go do some iteration on
and I want you to just take 45 minutes
and really iterate hard,
change as many things as you want.
And again, we haven't covered any
of this stuff in the lessons,
we haven't talked
specifically about typography
or colors or imagery
or any of those things.
So I'm not gonna judge you
based on how these designs look,
I just want you to get into the flow
of a rapidly iterating,
trying out different concepts
when you think of them,
not just sitting still
and staring at one art board
for 10 minutes and thinking,
yeah, maybe I should do this,
maybe I shouldn't do this, whatever.
Just try it.
Fail left, fail right.
Every little thing that you can tweak,
make it too big, make it too
small, make it too spaced out,
make it not spaced out enough.
Kind of just start to feel
what is the acceptable range of values?
Because so many of the
things that we design,
boil down to all these
little lists of numbers.
Sizes.
Sizes of fonts, sizes of spacing, colors.
Colors as you're gonna see
are just a set of numbers too
we can change all those.
So start to just play with that,
start to get into the habit
of failing left, failing right,
trying things that are a
little bit too much one way,
too much the other way
but all the while keeping moving.
And then finally of course,
once you've done all this
set it aside, come back the next day
and then if you have
kind of favorite elements
maybe you combine them into one
and end up with something
that's far better
than what you would have
done with half the stress.
All right.
So that's your homework.
When you're done, you can post it
in the Student Community and
we'll see in the next lesson.